hello everyone I'm shadowproof's
managing editor Kevin gustola and we're
joined with uh John kiriaku former CIA
officer and he's been writing at reader
supported news about Jeffrey Sterling's
case so we're talking to him we want to
bring some more attention to what the
Bureau of Prisons is doing to Jeffrey so
thanks for joining us John happy to be
here thanks for having me
and so uh we recently published a letter
from Jeffrey Sterling at Shadow proof
and you've been following what's going
on with him in the prison so for people
who aren't aware is
summarize where things are at right now
he's suffering from some very severe
heart problems right Jeffrey has a very
uh long-standing serious heart
arrhythmia that necessitated a hospital
stay of more than four days about 10
years ago he was a candidate for a
pacemaker immediately before he was
incarcerated he didn't have time to uh
to have that pacemaker installed so he
went to prison with his pre-existing
heart condition as you can imagine uh
his his health has deteriorated in
prison
um I'm I know from first-hand experience
that prison Health Care is is dismal at
best and Jeffrey just seems to be
experiencing the worst of of Both Worlds
having a pre-existing condition and
having to have it treated in prison and
so he's had a series really over the
last month or so a series of um heart
episodes or incidents I think he's
calling them where um he experiences
arrhythmia tachycardia in some cases uh
he fainted in one case and had to be
carried on a stretcher to the medical
unit and he has literally been begging
to be taken to an outside cardiologist
for uh for an exam and um the prison
refused to approve such an exam until
very recently and even then when the
outside exam was finally approved after
Jeffrey had been Shackled
um hands and feet and taken to this
outside Medical Professional the prison
never gave that doctor his medical
records and so the doctor had no idea
what he was examining no idea what he
was supposed to be looking for and as a
result all Jeffrey ended up getting was
a prescription for a beta blocker
right and there's a few problems with
that I mean one if you're in shackles
you probably couldn't take the proper
tests because you're going to have an
elevated heart rate anyways because
you're in that uh sort of condition
and on top of that uh What Jeffrey is is
talking about and describing is symptoms
of atrial fibrillation and the a prison
is insistent that he does not have this
history it would seem uh from what
um from what Holly his wife has shared
they insist that he doesn't have this
serious condition so would you talk
about how the the prison is under this
or I guess whether they believe it or
not we don't know if they actually truly
believe this or not but what they're
doing publicly is putting on this face
that he's fabricating medical
information so would you address that
yeah um this is a common tactic used in
in the Bureau of Prisons it's called
malingering and uh if you are determined
to be malingering that is uh claiming uh
uh Health maladies that you don't have
you are subject to a disciplinary action
which includes
um being committed to solitary
confinement losing your visiting
privileges your your telephone
privileges your email privileges they
can really make your life miserable
um now why would they do that well they
do that because they don't want to treat
you they don't want to treat a prisoner
that has an expensive uh health problem
uh because they don't want to pay for it
now couple that with with the fact that
the Bureau of Prisons is a Dumping
Ground for failed medical professionals
and you have just a perfect storm uh it
is it is easier for the Bureau of
Prisons and certainly cheaper for the
Bureau of Prisons for a prisoner to die
in their custody than it is to treat
them over the course of a period of time
and uh from your experience so you were
incarcerated for uh what 24 months is
that 23 months yes 23 months and and
your experience in prison
probably reflects what what Jeffrey said
I mean exactly at the end of his letter
he wraps up saying uh truly uh to FCI
Englewood and the Bop the life of an
inmate is a cheap commodity
it is indeed in the short time that I
was incarcerated uh at FCI Loreto in
Pennsylvania four other prisoners died
and all four of them died of preventable
illnesses a couple of heart attacks and
and two cases of cancer in one case I
actually was friendly with with um with
the man he uh he lived in a room that
was directly across the hall from the
chapel where I worked and uh I used to
sit at the same table uh he and I sat at
the same table in the cafeteria so I
would stop by and say hello one time I
stopped by and he complained to me that
his back was just killing him and he had
gone to medical and uh they gave him
Tylenol and the Tylenol did nothing I
saw him a week or two later and he was
using a cane I saw him a week or two
after that and he was using a walker to
make a long story short I finally went
to the chaplain and I said chaplain this
poor guy is obviously in distress and
medical is not giving him anything other
than Tylenol they won't take him out for
an x-ray they certainly wouldn't pay for
an MRI they just kept giving him Tylenol
every time he would go to the medical
unit and they threatened him with a
malingering shot
so
um finally to his credit the the
chaplain went to the head of the medical
unit and said please give this guy an
exam they finally took him out to uh to
a hospital where he had an x-ray and it
was found to have stage four spinal
cancer and he died just a few weeks
later
so uh you know just to put a cherry on
top of this whole this whole story
just nights before this poor guy's death
uh the warden went to his room and said
that he would approve
um a compassionate release if the
prisoner signed
um an agreement to not Sue the Bureau of
Prisons and he refused to sign the
agreement and he died in his bunk in
prison
that's just typical of of Medical Care
in prisons across the country this
wasn't specific to Loreto it wasn't
specific to this one prisoner this is
what Jeffrey Sterling is up against and
it's not going to get any better
right and uh there's a it's it's
somewhat chilling when you think about
it I I shared with him a story you had
put in uh or some antidotes that you
would put in your last letter from
Loretto and how you had uh summarized
the problems with medical at Loretto and
uh I believe you told a story of one uh
prisoner in there who who had suffered
from something serious and he came back
with okay that's normal
um and he named this prisoner who he
called William and talked about how
William had died
um and it first from a situation very
similar to what Jeffrey is going through
right now so he has this very chilling
recent example of what could happen to
him so
um one other thing that's really
critical about Jeffrey's story is that
on September 17th he went and had a
meeting with medical and they're acting
like uh it didn't happen because he was
told told that he had elevated levels of
troponin which suggests that he probably
suffered some kind of a heart attack
yes
yeah this is also a typical of what the
Bureau of Prisons medical units across
the country will do
it's my own personal belief that uh the
medical uh staff member the the Public
Health Service staff member who examined
Jeffrey purposely did not include a
write-up of that appointment uh in
Jeffrey's records and it is really meant
to to cover himself in the event that
Jeffrey has a more serious heart attack
or dies while he's still in prison uh
you know I I spent 15 years with the CIA
Kevin and over the course of those those
years I had occasion to come into
contact many many times with medical
professionals from the U.S Public Health
Service and I found them to be just
terrific uh people good Medics committed
patriotic
I had exactly the opposite experience
when I was in prison I was shocked to
find that Public Health Service
professionals were the Physicians
assistants that were seeing prisoners
seeing patients every day these these
folks were the the dregs of the Public
Health Service these were the people who
just couldn't cut it anywhere else in
government and so they were dumped into
the prisons and I'll give you another
example when I first arrived at Loretto
we have a doctor about whom most of the
prisoners I knew spoke very highly and
about six months into my sentence he
resigned he didn't ask to be transferred
he resigned and went into private
practice because he said the Bureau of
Prisons would not allow him to treat
Prisoners the way he wanted to treat
them which meant to send them to outside
uh medical appointments to prescribe the
medications that he thought they needed
we had a period of about six months with
no doctor at all
and then after those six months they
hired a failed child psychiatrist who
had been asked to leave one of the major
teaching hospitals here in the United
States so really you get the worst of
the worst in the medical field don't
forget that half of all doctors graduate
in the bottom halfs of their class right
somebody's got to be ranked last in
their class in medical school and
frequently those doctors end up in
prisons
foreign
and so on top of all of what you just
shared uh is the duress and stress that
you go through as a as a family member
trying to communicate uh your uh your
needs so Holly uh the wife of of Jeffrey
has been calling the Bureau of Prisons
trying to impress upon them the Need For
assistance and um I guess share some of
what uh the Bureau of Prisons has been
telling her and how this uh compares to
well the way you were handled but I
guess I guess fortunately you were never
really in a situation like Jeffrey no I
I was fortunate I did have to go to an
outside uh appointment one time because
uh just one week into my sentence I
broke a finger and um and I I did
everything the way I was supposed to I
went to Medical I said I have a broken
finger and the physician's assistant the
PA from the Public Health Service said
no it's not broken I said listen I've
broken bones before I'm telling you it's
broken we went back and forth for for
more than two weeks finally 16 days
after I broke the finger he allowed me
to go uh to an outside hospital to have
a an x-ray I was Shackled just like
Jeffrey my hands were Shackled In Front
of Me my feet were Shackled so I could
only take baby steps and then my hands
and feet were chained to each other
um and I got my uh my x-ray and the
doctor said well it's broken it's broken
broken but there's nothing we can do it
because it's already begun healing
itself and so I'll never regain full use
of my finger it's just a pinky finger
it's no big deal with Jeffrey Sterling
it's his heart
and these these prison officials just
don't want to acknowledge the fact that
the guy has an illness a disease that
has to be treated or it's going to get
worse and it may get worse to the point
of death what Holly Sterling has been
doing
and I've encouraged this in my own
writing at reader supported news is uh
she's been contacting the Bureau of
prison's regional office in Denver and
she has spoken with an official there
who was really not helpful in any way
and in fact threatened Holly a couple of
times saying things like I don't have to
speak to you you know it's it's a favor
that I'm doing for you speaking to you I
don't have to tell you anything I don't
have to do anything for your husband
well that that's not going to help
anybody's situation to get into what
amounts to a pissing match uh with with
the wife of a prisoner if the guy has a
medical problem then fix it it's your
duty as a medical professional whether
you're in the Bureau of Prisons or not
it's your duty to get this thing taken
care of
but uh but they just they seem to be
willing to do only the bare minimum and
that's only when they're pushed now I
know from um
from uh responses to my own pieces on
reader supported news that uh about 150
people have called the regional office
in Denver to demand medical care for
Jeffrey and I think that it's pissed
them off a little bit now perhaps and I
like to think this is the truth perhaps
it's pissed them off enough that um that
it's pushed them into action
What Jeffrey certainly thinks that the
only reason he was able to see that
outside specialist was because of people
calling uh the bop and and in
conversations with Holly uh this is the
sort of pressure that they want to keep
up so you know it coincidentally I have
the numbers right here and I'll just
take a moment I'll do it again at the
end of the interview I mean we're almost
finished but but for the North Central
regional office you can dial
913-621-3939 or you can call FCI
Englewood the prison where Jeffrey's
being held and that's
303-763-4300 and so those are the
numbers and it's working because people
you know I guess talk about what your
experience was on the inside just to
emphasize what it was like knowing that
people were paying attention to your
case and that is a huge deal and it
gives you a lot of power to protect
yourself again against prison officials
I truly believe and I've written about
this that you and Brian sonnenstein at
Shadow proof and Jane Hampshire at
firedoglake.com before you well you were
there as well uh I believe that you
three in particular were responsible for
my safety uh in prison and I don't mean
my safety vis-a-vis other prisoners I
mean my safety vis-a-vis the prison
Administration I was in danger of being
put at one point into something called
diesel therapy because of my my writing
and blogging and it was because you
published that allegation and there were
something like 1600 calls to the
director of the Bureau of Prisons
demanding that I not be put into diesel
therapy that I wasn't and that the
warden the assistant Warden and most
importantly the guards kept their hands
off of me what diesel therapy is I'll
just say quickly is um if if the prison
has a Troublesome prisoner they'll put
him into what's called um
Transportation status so that means
they'll they'll put you on a bus and
send you to a Transportation Hub in my
case it would have been the the U.S
penitentiary in Canaan Pennsylvania now
you can sit there for two weeks or you
can sit there for up to six months then
they put you on a bus to let's say
Harrisburg Pennsylvania Airport and then
they fly you to another Transportation
Hub in Atlanta Georgia at the
penitentiary there eventually you make
your way to the the Central
Transportation Hub in uh Oklahoma City
Oklahoma and then maybe Yankton South
Dakota or Englewood or California or
wherever anywhere in America there there
are so many prisons the reason they do
that though is because when a prisoner
is in transportation status he does not
have access to a telephone to an email
or to pens and paper
and it's the only way really that they
can legally silence someone
and transport status Transportation
status can last up to a year you can be
in transportation status for that long
well I only had something like a year
left on my sentence and uh and they were
talking about ways to get me to stop
writing I have no doubt in my mind
that at FCI Englewood they have had
similar conversations about how to
silence Jeffrey Sterling
uh and I do believe that when I was
talking to Holly she mentioned something
about uh not just Jeffrey but the entire
unit where Jeffrey is being confined
being told that they would lose email
privileges uh mostly on a whim just an
arbitrary whim that this prison official
was upset about something someone did
and was willing to take that means of
communication away so it doesn't need I
mean that's how quickly you can lose
your connection so my last question is
the Demand right now it's just it's to
focus on what people should be if
they're interested in supporting Jeffrey
and and contributing to this outside
pressure uh what they need to do is
impress upon the officials that he needs
a certain thing a holly believes that
that demand should be seeing an outside
doctor the prison can't take care of
this issue they've already failed
Jeffrey they will continue to fail him
uh what do you think about her her
attitude especially based on your
experience
yeah I think Holly Sterling is is uh
exactly on point uh the the prison has
already proven several times that they
are either unable or unwilling to help
Jeffrey Sterling the only way that he
can be treated properly and
appropriately is by an outside
specialist and that's really what we all
have to push for
all right John I'm just going to read
these numbers so people have them again
uh if you would like to call the
facility and help out Jeffrey the Bureau
of Prisons North Central regional office
which Colorado is under is
913-621-3939 FCI Englewood the facility
where Jeffrey is being held is
303-763-4300 so and again thank you John
for joining us we really appreciate it
happy to do it thanks for having me